<!-- $Id$ -->

<Chapter Label="Examples">
<Heading>Examples of &SCSCP; usage</Heading>    

In this chapter we are going to demonstrate some examples of communication
between client and server using the SCSCP.

<Section Label="ProvidingServices">
<Heading>Providing services with the SCSCP package</Heading>

You can try to run the SCSCP server with the configuration file
<File>scscp/example/myserver.g</File>. To do this, go to that directory
and enter <C>gap myserver.g</C>. After this you will see some diagnostic
messages and finally the server will be waiting for the connection. The
final part of the startup screen will look as follows:

<Example>
<![CDATA[
#I  Installed SCSCP procedure Factorial
#I  Installed SCSCP procedure WS_Factorial
#I  Installed SCSCP procedure GroupIdentificationService
#I  Installed SCSCP procedure IdGroup512ByCode
#I  Installed SCSCP procedure WS_IdGroup
#I  Installed SCSCP procedure WS_Karatsuba
#I  Installed SCSCP procedure EvaluateOpenMathCode
#I  Ready to accept TCP/IP connections at localhost:26133 ...
#I  Waiting for new client connection at localhost:26133 ...
]]>
</Example>

See further self-explanatory comments in the file 
<File>scscp/example/myserver.g</File>.
There also some test files in the directory <File>scscp/tst/</File>
supplied with detailed comments. First, you may use demonstration
files, preliminary loading the code for the demonstration mode as it is
explained in these files, or just executing step by step each command
from <File>scscp/tst/demo.g</File> and <File>scscp/tst/omdemo.g</File>.
Then you can try to use client's tools to access SCSCP services from 
files <File>scscp/tst/id512.g</File>, <File>scscp/tst/idperm.g</File> 
and <File>scscp/tst/factor.g</File>.
</Section>

<Section Label="Id512">
<Heading>Identifying groups of order 512</Heading>

We will give an example guiding you through all steps
of creation of your own &SCSCP; service.
<P/>

The &GAP; Small Group Library does not provide identification for
groups of order 512 using the function <C>IdGroup</C>:

<Example>
<![CDATA[
gap> IdGroup( DihedralGroup( 256 ) );
[ 256, 539 ]
gap> IdGroup(DihedralGroup(512)); 
Error, the group identification for groups of size 
512 is not available called from
<function>( <arguments> ) called from read-eval-loop
Entering break read-eval-print loop ...
you can 'quit;' to quit to outer loop, or
you can 'return;' to continue
brk> 
]]>
</Example>

However, the &GAP; package &ANUPQ; <Cite Key="ANUPQ"/> has a function
<C>IdStandardPresented512Group</C> that does this work as demonstrated
below:
 
<Example>
<![CDATA[
gap> LoadPackage("anupq");
-------------------------------------------------------------
Loading ANUPQ 3.0 (ANU p-Quotient package)
C code by  Eamonn O'Brien <obrien@math.auckland.ac.nz>
           (ANU pq binary version: 1.8)
GAP code by Werner Nickel <nickel@mathematik.tu-darmstadt.de>
        and   Greg Gamble  <gregg@math.rwth-aachen.de>

            For help, type: ?ANUPQ
-------------------------------------------------------------
true
gap> G := DihedralGroup( 512 );            
<pc group of size 512 with 9 generators>
gap> F := PqStandardPresentation( G );
<fp group on the generators [ f1, f2, f3, f4, f5, f6, f7, f8, f9 ]>
gap> H := PcGroupFpGroup( F );
<pc group of size 512 with 9 generators>
gap> IdStandardPresented512Group( H );
[ 512, 2042 ]
]]>
</Example>

The package &ANUPQ; requires <Package>UNIX</Package> environment 
and it is natural to provide an identification service for groups of
order 512 to make it available for other platforms.

Now we need to decide how the client will transmit a group to the server.
How the group should be encoded in the &OpenMath;? Should we convert it
to a permutation representation to be able to use existing content dictionaries?
However, the &SCSCP; protocol provides enough freedom for the user
to select its own data representation, and since we are linking together 
two copies of the same system, we may use the <E>pcgs code</E> to pass the
data to the server. 

First we create a function accepting the integer number that is the code for 
pcgs of a group of order 512 and returning the number of this group in the
GAP Small Groups library:

<Example>
<![CDATA[
IdGroup512ByCode := function( code )
local G, F, H;
G := PcGroupCode( code, 512 );
F := PqStandardPresentation( G );H := PcGroupFpGroup( F );return IdStandardPresented512Group( H );
end;
]]>
</Example>

After such function was created on the server, we need to make it
<Q>visible</Q> as an &SCSCP; procedure:

<Example>
<![CDATA[
gap> InstallSCSCPprocedure("IdGroup512", IdGroup512ByCode );
InstallSCSCPprocedure : procedure IdGroup512 installed. 
]]>
</Example>

Note that this function assumes that the argument is a valid code
for some group of order 512, and we wish the client to make it
sure that this is the case. To do this, and also for the client's
convenience, we provide the client's counterpart for this 
service. Here the group must be a pc-group of order 512, otherwise
an error message will appear.

<Example>
<![CDATA[
IdGroup512:=function( G )
local code, result;
if Size( G ) <> 512 then
  Error( "G must be a group of order 512 \n" );
fi;
code := CodePcGroup( G );
result := EvaluateBySCSCP( "IdGroup512ByCode", [ code ], 
                           "localhost", 26133 );
return result.object;
end;
]]>
</Example>

Now the client can call the function <C>IdGroup512</C>, and the procedure
of getting result is as simple as the usage of <C>IdGroup</C> for those
groups for which it works:

<Example>
<![CDATA[
gap> IdGroup512(DihedralGroup(512));
#I  Creating a socket ...
#I  Connecting to a remote socket via TCP/IP ...
#I  Got connection initiation message
#I  Request sent ...
#I  Waiting for reply ...
[ 512, 2042 ]
]]>
</Example>

</Section>

</Chapter>