<Chapter Label="Preface">
<Heading>Preface</Heading>    

The &GAP; package &SCSCP; implements the Symbolic 
Computation Software Composability protocol <Cite Key="SCSCP"/>. This
protocol specifies an &OpenMath;-based remote procedure call framework, in which
all messages (procedure calls and returns of results of successful computation
or error messages) are encoded in &OpenMath; using content dictionaries 
&scscp1; and &scscp2; (<Cite Key="scscp1cd"/>, <Cite Key="scscp2cd"/>).
Using the &SCSCP; package, &GAP; can communicate locally or remotely with any 
other &OpenMath;-enabled &SCSCP;-compliant application which may be not only 
another computer algebra system but also another instance of the &GAP; system
or even, for example, an external Java or C/C++ application via libraries
<URL>http://java.symcomp.org/</URL> 
or <URL>http://www.imcce.fr/Equipes/ASD/trip/scscp/</URL>
providing an &SCSCP; API. Such communication will go into seamless manner 
for the &GAP; user, since all conversions from &GAP; to &OpenMath; and
vice versa will be performed in the background. See the SCIEnce project
homepage <URL>http://www.symbolic-computing.org/</URL> for the details
about computer algebra systems and other sotware supporting &SCSCP;
<P/>

The &SCSCP; package for &GAP; has two main components:
<List>
<Item>SCSCP server;</Item>
<Item>SCSCP client.</Item>
</List>

There are several ways to start &GAP; &SCSCP; server:
<List>
    <Item>call <Ref Func="RunSCSCPserver" /> from the &GAP; session specifying the 
        server name and the port number from the &GAP; session;
    </Item>
    <Item>start &GAP; as <C>gap myserver.g</C>, where <File>myserver.g</File>
        is the server configuration file with the last command being the call 
        of <Ref Func="RunSCSCPserver" /> (an example of such configuration file 
        is given in <File>scscp/example/myserver.g</File> );
    </Item>
    <Item>start &GAP; as a daemon using the script <File>gapd.sh</File> which
        is supplied in the root directory of the package (for the description
        of all available options see comments in <File>gapd.sh</File>).
    </Item>
</List>

During startup the server installs all procedures that it will provide and 
loads their lookup mechanisms, and then begins to listen to the specified 
port. The recommended port number is 26133 which has been assigned to SCSCP 
by the Internet Assigned Numbers Authority (IANA) in November 2007, see 
<URL>http://www.iana.org/assignments/port-numbers</URL>.
<P/>

When the server accepts a connection from client, it starts the 
"accept-evaluate-return" loop:
<List>
<Item>accepts the <C>"procedure&uscore;call";</C> message;</Item>
<Item>performs lookup of the appropriate GAP function;</Item>
<Item>evaluates the result (or produces a side-effect);</Item>
<Item>returns the result in the <C>"procedure&uscore;completed"</C> message
    or returns an error in the <C>"procedure&uscore;terminated"</C> message.</Item>
</List>

The server works in a "multi-user" mode. When one client is connected, 
the server is busy for other clients. As soon as the computation is finished 
and the client is disconnected, the server is waiting for the next connection, 
and normally it never stops until it will be terminated by the service provider. 
The server maintain a queue of five incoming connections (this parameter
can be easily modified), and on each iteration evaluates the next request from the queue.
<P/>

There is an &SCSCP; server accessible at <File>scscp.gap-system.org</File>, 
port 26133. It is running under development versions of the &GAP; system and a selection
of currently distributed packages. The reader is encouraged to try to use examples from
the manual to access this service, replacing <File>"localhost"</File> by its address,
where appropriate. Please report to Alexander Konovalov if you will discover any bugs
or if the server seems not available.
<P/>
    
The SCSCP client:
<List>
<Item>establishes connection with the specified server at the specified port;</Item>
<Item>sends the <C>"procedure&uscore;call"</C> message to the server;</Item>
<Item>waits for the result of the computation or returns to pick it up later;</Item>
<Item>fetches the response, extracting the result from the 
    <C>"procedure&uscore;completed"</C> message or entering the break loop in the 
    case of the <C>"procedure&uscore;terminated"</C> message.
</Item>
</List>

On the top of this functionality we built a set of instructions for simple 
parallel computations framework using the &SCSCP; protocol, which allows
to send several procedure calls in parallel and then collect all results or 
pick up the first available result, and implements the master-worker skeleton. 
These tools are presented in the Chapter <Ref Label="Parallel"/>.
<P/>

The package also implements a new kind of &GAP; input-output streams, namely
input-output TCP streams (see Chapter <Ref Label="UsingStreams"/>), based on the 
functionality for TCP/IP protocol usage provided by the &GAP; package &IO;.
Such streams may constitute an independent interest for adapting streams-using &GAP; 
code to use streams across the network.
<P/>

Finally, the manual describes how the communication by &SCSCP; goes between 
several instances of the &GAP; system, but the same behaviour is expected 
from any &SCSCP;-compliant application: the set of supported &OpenMath;
symbols clearly will be different, but the rules of communication are
precisely specified in the &SCSCP; specification <Cite Key="SCSCP"/>. See
the homepage of the SCIEnce project <URL>http://www.symbolic-computing.org/</URL>
for the information about &SCSCP;-compliant computer algebra systems
and other tools developed in the project.

</Chapter>